Guide to the Calvin Pollard Architectural Drawing Collection 1834-1852, undated PR 51
New-York Historical Society
Calvin Pollard Architectural Drawing Collection
1834-1852, undated
New-York Historical Society
PR 51
0.25 Linear feet (ca. 84 sheets of drawings, 2 albums)
The collection consists of architectural and engineering drawings, chiefly elevations and floor plans in ink, graphite, and color wash. Despite the fact that few clients or specific locales are identified and only about 10 drawings are signed or dated, the rarity of original designs from this time period makes the Society's drawings valuable.
Provenance
Gifts of E. H. Sauer, 1913, and Samuel V. Hoffman, 1912 and 1917.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Calvin Pollard was born on June 14, 1797, in New Braintree, Massachusetts. He moved with his family to Cazenovia, in central New York State, in 1803, and then to New York City in 1818. Pollard first appears in the city directories in 1826 as a builder. He then is listed consistently from 1830 until his death in 1850, changing occupational listings from "builder" to "architect" in 1840.
Pollard's New York City Directory Listings
1826 - builder - 23 Thompson Street
1830-1833 - builder - 23 Thompson Street
1833-1838 - builder - 28 Thompson Street
1838-1839 - builder - 4 Wall Street, house 97 Nineteenth Street
1839-1840 - builder - 4 Wall Street, house 214 Nineteenth Street
1840-1841 - architect - 6 Broad Street, house 214 Nineteenth Street
1841-1845 - architect - 6 Broad Street, house 214 West Nineteenth Street
1845-1847 - architect - 4 Broad Street, house 214 West Nineteenth Street
1847-1848 - architect - 14 Pine Street, house 214 West Nineteenth Street
1848-1850 - architect - 5 Broad Street, house 214 West Nineteenth Street
Scope and Content Note
The Calvin Pollard Architectural Drawing Collection contains more than 120 drawings for buildings spanning the period from 1834 to 1849. Drawings are chiefly elevations and floor plans in ink, graphite, and color wash. Many of Pollard's designs are in the Greek Revival style.
Despite the fact that few clients or specific locales are identified and only about ten drawings are signed or dated, the rarity of original designs from this time period makes Pollard's drawings valuable. For example, plans for some fifteen residential projects provide data for studying the development of the typical New York townhouse.
All drawings are filed by number and reflect a general grouping by building type: residences, commercial properties, churches, theatres, and miscellaneous buildings. The latter group includes an 1834 plan for the base of a proposed Washington Monument in New York and a lunatic asylum. Projects also include a business establishment and a residence for a Mr. Hamlin; a commercial building in Manhattan and a residence in Ossining, New York, for a Dr. Brandreth; the Fort Washington Hotel; and Christ Church on Anthony (now Worth) Street.
The collection also contains two discrete albums, one containing nine pages of drawings titled "Plans and Elevations of the New National Theatre C. Pollard 1840." It holds contract drawings for the reconstruction the theatre following the great 1835 New York fire.
The second album holds nine engineering drawings that date from 1841-1852, with five additional drawings are laid in; all are technical drawings of railroad bridges, carriage parts, tunnels, and canal locks for transportation lines in Pennsylvania. Formerly assumed to be the work of Calvin Pollard, they are now thought to be the work of his son Don Alonzo Pollard (1837-1908), a civil engineer who was active in the construction of the Delaware, Lackawanna and Western Railroad.
Most of the architectural drawings are described in George S. Koyl, editor, American Architectural Drawings... to 1917 (Philadelphia: American Institute of Architects Philadelphia Chapter, 1969.)
Arrangement
All drawings are filed by an N-YHS assigned number and reflect a general grouping by building type.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
A lithographic print of Pollard's full design for the Washington Monument can be found in the Print Room's Portrait File (PR 052) under Washington, George: Monuments and Memorials. Pollard's pocket diaries for 1841 and 1842, as well as a contract for remodeling Castle Garden, are held in the Manuscript Department of the New-York Historical Society Library. A watercolor rendering by Pollard of the Henry Remsen residence is in the Department of Paintings, Sculpture, and Decorative Arts of the Society's Museum.
Tunnels -- New York (State).; Locks (Hydraulic engineering); Architectural drawings (visual works); Technical drawings; Contract drawings; Commercial buildings -- United States -- Designs and plans.; Elevations (orthographic projections).; Floor plans.; Albums; Watercolors (paintings); Greek revival (Architecture) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Dwellings -- New York (State).; Architecture, Domestic -- United States.; Architecture, American -- 19th century -- Designs and plans.; Public buildings -- United States -- Design and plans.; Asylums; Railroad bridges -- New York (State).; New National Theatre (New York, N.Y.); Pollard, Don Alonzo, 1837-1908
- unspecified
  Scope and Contents note
  Drawings are arranged in five groups: Residences, Commercial Properties, Churches, Theatres, and Miscellaneous Buildings. Consult the database printouts in the Society's Print Room for specific drawing titles.
  - Residences
    General note
    See also Folder 23, drawing 45.
    - Unidentified row houses, drawing numbers 1-4, undated (Box Unknown container 722 for instance of Unidentified row houses, drawing numbers 1-4, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified row houses, drawing numbers 5-8, 1834, undated (Box Unknown container 723 for instance of Unidentified row houses, drawing numbers 5-8, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified row house, 28th Street, Manhattan, drawing number 9, 1845 (Box Unknown container 724 for instance of Unidentified row house, 28th Street, Manhattan, drawing number 9, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified row house, drawing number 10, 1847 (Box Unknown container 725 for instance of Unidentified row house, drawing number 10, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified detached houses, drawing numbers 11-13, undated (Box Unknown container 726 for instance of Unidentified detached houses, drawing numbers 11-13, Folder 5)
    - Brandreth residence, Ossining, New York, drawing number 14, [1841] (Box Unknown container 727 for instance of Brandreth residence, Ossining, New York, drawing number 14, Folder 6)
    - Detached houses, including Moffat residence, 335 Broadway, drawing numbers 15-17, 1844, undated (Box Unknown container 728 for instance of Detached houses, including Moffat residence, 335 Broadway, drawing numbers 15-17, Folder 7)
  - Commercial Properties
    - Buildings, New York City, including Brandreth building at 241 Broadway, drawing numbers 18-22, 1838-1849, undated (Box Unknown container 729 for instance of Buildings, New York City, including Brandreth building at 241 Broadway, drawing numbers 18-22, Folder 8)
    - Hamlin stores and residence, Eighth Avenue, Fourth Street, and Jane Street, drawing numbers 23-24, 1847 (Box Unknown container 730 for instance of Hamlin stores and residence, Eighth Avenue, Fourth Street, and Jane Street, drawing numbers 23-24, Folder 9)
    - Hotel, Wall Street, drawing number 25, undated (Box Unknown container 731 for instance of Hotel, Wall Street, drawing number 25, Folder 10)
  - Churches
    - Christ Church, Anthony (now Worth) Street, drawing number 26, 1847 (Box Unknown container 732 for instance of Christ Church, Anthony (now Worth) Street, drawing number 26, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified church, drawing number 27, undated (Box Unknown container 733 for instance of Unidentified church, drawing number 27, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified church, Manhattan, drawing number 28, undated (Box Unknown container 734 for instance of Unidentified church, Manhattan, drawing number 28, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified church, drawing number 29, 1849 (Box Unknown container 735 for instance of Unidentified church, drawing number 29, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified church, drawing number 30, 1843 (Box Unknown container 736 for instance of Unidentified church, drawing number 30, Folder 15)
  - Theatres
    - Unidentified, Broadway and Mercer Street, drawing numbers 31-32, 1847, undated (Box Unknown container 737 for instance of Unidentified, Broadway and Mercer Street, drawing numbers 31-32, Folder 16-17)
    - Unidentified, drawing number 33, undated (Box Unknown container 738 for instance of Unidentified, drawing number 33, Folder 18)
    - New National Theatre, Church Street [album], drawing number 34, 1840 (Box Unknown container 739 for instance of New National Theatre, Church Street [album], drawing number 34, Folder 19)
    - Theaters and/or commercial buildings, unidentified, drawing numbers 35-39, 1847, undated (Box Unknown container 740 for instance of Theaters and/or commercial buildings, unidentified, drawing numbers 35-39, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous buildings
    - Buildings, unidentified, including one on Mercer Street, drawing numbers 40-41, undated (Box Unknown container 741 for instance of Buildings, unidentified, including one on Mercer Street, drawing numbers 40-41, Folder 21)
    - Lunatic Asylum, Fort Washington Hotel and an unidentified building on Duane Street, drawing numbers 42-43, undated (Box Unknown container 742 for instance of Lunatic Asylum, Fort Washington Hotel and an unidentified building on Duane Street, drawing numbers 42-43, Folder 22)
    - Plan for Washington Monument, and unidentified residence, drawing numbers 44-45, 1834, undated (Box Unknown container 743 for instance of Plan for Washington Monument, and unidentified residence, drawing numbers 44-45, Folder 23)
  - Engineering drawings [album of drawings by Don Alonzo Pollard], drawing numbers E1-E9, 1841-1852, undated (Box Unknown container 744 for instance of Engineering drawings [album of drawings by Don Alonzo Pollard], drawing numbers E1-E9, Folder 24)